alright here we go here's the second
episode of lighting directors commentary
my guest today is jeff waffle from
Humphries McGee has gone Jeff it is
going great thanks for having me on your
big program look so this is the first
song of the second set and I point that
out because I try to have kind of a
build theme Attica Lee over the course
of the night there are certain cues that
I try not to ever go to in the first set
and then the idea is that you know the
show builds an intensity
the only problem with that is that the
setlist is different every night so what
happens if the band comes out and opens
with a song that they typically would
close the second set with you're kind of
stuck but all of us improv guys kind of
deal with the same thing you got to save
your tricks so now I know okay the
gloves are off I can kind of do whatever
I want here is a little bit more of a
relaxed vibe the crowd has also been you
know settling into the venue lubricated
you know they just stepped outside for
set break or whatever they're into no
judgement but I I can't always feel
there's a little bit of different vibe
second set or a major majorly different
vibe
so are you look ready right now you know
what look you're gonna go do I do it's
probably not always the same I know this
is what we call DBK they're bleeding you
cotton which never heard a member I'm
free say we just say DBK I know it's
gonna be kind of a hot look but it could
be a different hot look night tonight
and there's obviously lots of blue and
that so it to be arguably ambivalent so
here I'm on the right-hand screen what
I'm doing there is I'm selecting
different page views and each page view
has ten cues and I try to lay them out
on the board left to right in a way that
makes sense to me with more of the
bright looks on the left-hand side and
more of the pretty purple blue looks on
the right so now Joel comes in he sings
Brendan and him are trading lyrics here
are lines and so I try to light them up
pretty straightforward
that was one of the songs that took me a
long time to learn because there's a lot
of different sections I also picked this
song because you can't really see them
but our esteemed lighting crew chief
Louie is to my left you can see him a
little bit later on and the caff theater
has video projection on the wall now I
would never use video projection just
because it's not part of our show and in
order to run it you have to rely on a
house projectionist and so you know I'm
very protective of hitting every note
perfectly and it's impossible to have a
total stranger who's never been owned up
who's McGee show hit all those changes
so but you also have to utilize the
technology that's there and the capital
theater owner Peter Shapiro a good
friend of ours good friend of the band
she is very ended like the technology
that he wants to use so you do it for
Pete it's like kind of thing any other
venue in the world it's like hey we want
you to use this to be like no wait a man
it's not our show but for Pete you know
he invested I think he had mark Brickman
actually designed that video projection
that Mark Brickman was the lighting
designer for Pink Floyd for the Homer
David Gilmour it basically everyone so
you'll see in a little bit when we get
to the improv section I start calling
hues to Louie and Louie is on a headset
calling the cue then relaying them to
the guy backstage which is something
that's totally outside of our comfort
zone the biggest thing for me when I do
lighting is this is all muscle memories
so you're see I'm not even looking at
the stage the stage is like an
afterthought because I'm concentrating
on what I'm doing so to add in another
production element of that and have to
communicate it verbally
a challenge so this time around Chris
Myers comes in it took me probably five
years to figure out is there's so much
going on like oh I should light up Chris
only on the third verse I collect those
little subtleties er there was another
section of this song that I apparently
struggled with for years I didn't
realize it but one of the things that um
fries does is they write really complex
time signatures into their songs but
when executed correctly it sounds like
it's in 4/4 so this part coming up right
here you can watch my mouth move I'm
counting it 1 2 3 4 next time it comes
around 23 1 2 3
it skips a beat if I don't say it out
loud I forget 1 2 3 4
Brian states like our bass player pulled
me aside on the tour bus and one night
about 3 morning he's like dude that last
sections in 3 you get it wrong every
time - Shay boss I'll never get her
funky again quite a quite a learning
curve with um fries and by the way that
doesn't happen very often that the band
members pull me aside it's probably
happened twice in 10 years but I
appreciate it
there was another time where the song is
rocker - there's a part in the beginning
where Jake and Brendan or trading Lex
and I couldn't figure out what the time
signature wasn't like after you know
five years
I asked Brendan I said what time sooner
is that and he's like oh it's not in the
time signature idea it's just a visual
cue I said okay he's like but you can't
see because it's just our eyes so now he
kind of Telegraph's it
all right so here we're coming to I
think there's a big peak here so I'm
right I'm going to a high position I
went to white by accident there I'd
rather go to white on the big hit right
here
[Music]
if you're not a big um freezing Magee
fan this up until this point this has
all still been composed there hasn't
been really a note of improv
I mean maybe here they're like with a
cue you just hit what was the thought
process that guy you depressing that cue
but the big white one toe just now well
you would be blacked out and hit a new
cue just trying to get to something that
who's gonna be in purple and I'm
probably gonna bring up a big look with
a bunch of cone gobos because I know
it's a pretty section and that's
something I do a lot you know to kind of
reset right so Brendon here plays this
riff and then Andy comes in with the the
wind chimes I don't know if that's the
technical term but the chimes and I just
looked over to my left that's Louie I
said hey get ready here comes the Improv
tell your guy on the head you know the
poor guy we should just pepper them all
night we're like no I said slow or
faster so here I told them get ready
stand by for the video projectionists
here's our pretty look and now this is
the first open section of the song so
now you can see me I'm gonna start
leaning over to Louie and giving him
instructions and we you know I had the
foresight to say hey we need a camera
for the video projection but there
literally was no physical place where we
could mount a camera to see it because
we were underneath the balcony yeah I
was gonna say to you oh you don't have
three cameras on this so now we just
rolled in the video projection I said
hey that looks good and I remember
specifically I think the first night is
what I wanted to record this on the
second night the first night saying you
know we need to approach this we need
everything to be real really slow we
want everything moving very slowly
because I feel like with most production
yeah I keep doing that with my hand slow
down tell him to slow it down and then
he goes over the radio the projection
he's slowing the rate of the projections
down yes like if you think about a you
know water because I tried to go for a
lot of organic things because there's a
lot of different video cues to choose
from and some of them look a little too
like Tron a little too cartoony or or
purposely to psychedelic you know I
think like like raindrops if you capture
them in the right way can be way more
psychedelic than like some
Paisley some [ __ ] windows
screensaver yes exactly try not to look
like a screen saver but I have no idea
what I'm saying Tim there I just I can
see it on my face that this is like the
most stressful thing I've ever done but
yet the most fun I've also it's such a
weird bounce I'm sure you can relate to
that oh yeah absolutely
the other thing that I see here and I've
watched this a couple of times right
like there's a long stretches of time
where I'm not like looking at the show
and I think that's that's important for
aspiring young lbz you want to know the
music so cold that it's like the last
thing on your mind it's just ingrained
in the DNA like I know I can hear the
little nuances of the way they improvise
I can tell when they're gonna come to
the next big yeah oh wait you probably
know what looking to that but currently
it's not like yeah surprised itself so
you can see my left hand here
those are color wipes or they were and
on my right hand these are what we call
flash buttons so if I hold down the
button it goes to white if I let go it
goes back to whatever color I was
previously in and the reason I run it
that way is I've literally been you know
we talked about muscle memory I've been
executing fuse like that for over 20
years because when I first was using
regular park ends it's the same gesture
so I wanted to kind of keep that
familiarity so I have on my right hand
there they're all colors
my left in there those are my intensity
faders so if I was gonna black out the
show I would take those down
I think it's funny that I like I'm
taking this so seriously as it in the
grand scheme of life this is somehow
important but at the moment there's
nothing more important but looking at it
now it's kind of funny
[Applause]
so at this point I have no idea what's
coming next I know we're in a mellow
section we're in an open section but the
band members may be talking to each
other on a on their in ear monitors they
have a talkback mics that I can hear I'm
wearing in-ear monitors buried somewhere
underneath all that hair and they may be
saying something like hey let's do that
a B section we worked on earlier in
which case I believe that would be
denoted as a Jimmy Stewart which is that
you can google that but that's the term
we give to our open and props then
there's also jazz Odysseys and I'm sure
I'm pretty spans will email me but I
still don't really know the difference I
think it jazz Odyssey goes on maybe a
little longer or something Jimmy
Stewart's maybe tend to be pre-written
sections that they'll work on during
rehearsal that day and it's not they're
not practicing how to improv they're
just saying this is the a section it's
gonna be in a minor key and then the B
section is gonna be double time and a
major key it's that those are the only
parameters but it allows them all to
kind of move seamlessly so now I'm kind
of trying to get a feel of like where
we're gonna go with this thing guys and
I'm trying to create as many different
pulses so for example you see the towers
behind the band and that kind of
ghosting white pulse
when everything's clicking perfectly I
try to have the tempo of that be
following the bass for example and then
have the tempo of the rest of the rig
following maybe the hi-hat it doesn't
always happen but every now and then you
get three or four different attributes
matching different members of the band
and that's always kind of the goal so
now I'm saying okay I'm gonna do my
projection on the back wall with my
lights let's get the video projection
going and one of the things we did
between night 1 and I 2 is we went
through and we picked out video
projections that were I don't know the
right way to say this but the entire
venue was all one screen so if we're
looking at an image of the ocean the
entire room would be that picture that
full-size picture of the ocean because
there's multiple projectors so there are
certain cues that they have where each
projector outputs so you'd see like 6
different ocean looks or that's not
gonna stitch them all together it's just
yeah I like it when like you look like
you're in a Romney dome you know like if
you want to go see Everest if the
omni-flex
so I don't know what we're doing but I
would assume it'd be some slow moving
kind of dripping watery you know I think
like I said nature can be way more
psychedelic than people trying to be
psychedelic but I grew up on Cape Cod so
I may be biased
so you'll see here it gets it starts to
get a little bit more intense and I'll
be doing this thing with my left hand
which is like what the television
producers do to say you know keep going
we have time to Phil and I apparently I
think that made me feel comfortable
because I it's again I'd probably do it
20 times and I'm probably just telling
Lily keep doing what you're doing which
is redundant because they're not gonna
stop until I say stop but I need some
semblance of a routine here because I'm
Way out of my routine and that's that's
kind of why I picked this song because
I'm Way out of my element here I'd like
to add a whole other dimension of like
having to communicate you have to keep
going turn your hand that'll that'll
help Jeff take over over the show
benefited from it oh absolutely but it
it takes me way out of my comfort zone
which is a good thing and it's good to
challenge yourself but if we toured with
video projection it would be part of my
muscle memory
there's that hand gesture again but the
fact that we do it once a year means
that it's like it just forces you to do
something different
it would be like if you see if I can
come up with a metaphor here I was gonna
say I would be like if you played piano
your entire life and then suddenly you
know you had to play like with a third
arm play a synthesizer I don't know so
here this is a full rig dimmer chase and
like I said at this point I'm kind of on
autopilot with the light show which I
don't I don't love to have to do that
but I only have one brain and I'm trying
to direct the video projections well and
you also done this kind of lit this kind
of jam a thousand times Witter literally
probably over a thousand so I'm not this
specific song but yeah over the course
of I think I've been doing lights now
for more than 20 years and just like
they don't have to think about every
note it's the exact same thing yes it's
exactly thing as a musician not having
to think about it and you hear that in
any art form you sit and hear these
people like Carlos Santana or Trey
Anastasio these people talk about like
the goal is always to get to a point
where you're not thinking which I feel
like I get to that point on a good night
not every night but that's why the video
projection thing is such a challenges
because by definition I have to be
thinking about I totally related but
kind of separate media medium and so
[Music]
it definitely keeps me on my game here
and I always I always tell Louie he's
the sweetest guy I always say to him
please don't take it personally if I
seem like I'm yelling at you I'm just in
the moment I'm not yelling I'm not mad
I'm just I'm trying to get my thoughts
in my head into your head into the guy
backstage his head instantaneously so I
always go out of my way to like
high-five I'm after a big jam you'll see
I fist bump him look
positive reinforcement like I'm doing
great man leadership skills and the
video projection is here at the cap with
a guy I'd never worked with before I've
worked with the regular guy
quote-unquote the normal full-time guy a
bunch of times and he's really good he's
very intuitive this guy had never worked
it before and he was he was really good
to work with the first night we had to
kind of work our communication but I
felt like we sat down the second day we
went over it and we really gelled and
now we're back into another composed
section so when when it goes to that
movement effect is that all built into
one cue like yellow slow-moving effect
um you'll see my right hand there I'm
actually holding down the yellow this
this cue is more of an orange okay so
there's a cute but in the cue it's
rotating with the movement effect and
it's only yellow because you're holding
gun the flash right yeah it's one of
those things like I have so many cues
when I wrote that cue for some reason I
put in orange from the color wheel and I
just never changed it but a lot of times
when I go to it I'll press without
getting too technical here for my mom
who has no idea what we're talking about
in this half of audience doesn't dig on
me not on you oh it's true but uh when
you because the color wheel doesn't
respond the same way yeah if I want to
change colors a lot there's a little bit
of latency because of the physicality of
the color wheel so if I press that
yellow that's a see my
and now we're starting this is still I
would consider this kind of this is an
improv I mean it's improv but the the
section is constant in this song sure
it's generally the same the progression
is yeah so the obviously the guitar solo
is is improv and they individually know
to expect as a permanent entity yeah
there's a set number of measures here
the other part was what we would call
open for anything can happen and they'll
probably be another open section if I
recall honestly I can't keep this song
as there's so many sections it's all
sure enough I'm sure but it looks like
we're coming up to a big peak here and I
love that I look like Beyonce with the
fan in my hair and the white light
tipped to clarify only my the movement
of my hair reminds me of Beyonce but I
just we call it the Beyonce fan yeah
[Applause]
and now I think we're gonna break it
down again yep and you see me
frantically with my left hand that's
where I keep all my speed faders so I
can adjust oh we're done we're out of
time
look at that our apologies to Matt Damon
thank you for having me we ran out of
time
sorry Matt we'll get you next time